And I knew for a fact with certainty
that I never ever wanted to consider
IC7. And here we are.
>> This is Marius Schultz. He grew to a
senior staff engineer or IC7 at Meta by
redefining expectations three times. And
he shared everything he learned along
the way.
>> There's an IC4, IC5, and IC6 and maybe
even higher way to go about almost any
problem.
>> He got another redefined expectations
rating promo to IC7. The year that
threads launched, I think I I came up
just under 2,000 diffs at the end of the
year
>> for a year. [laughter]
>> He also opened up about what held his
career back. Why was there no promotion
in the greatly exceeds case?
>> I think at the end of the day, it came
down to one expectations [music] miss
that blocked the promo. Have the
expectations of the highest levels ever
scared you? [music] Here's the full
episode.
you chose a specialty of like being a
front-end engineer like what's the
thinking there?
>> I have this burning passion for the web
as corny as that sounds. I don't know
where it comes from. I just know that
I've always had it and most people
who've worked with me um have probably
seen that. Yeah. Working with me over
the years. I've always been a fan of web
development. I've always enjoyed doing
it and um I've been doing it for a long
time at this point. I started getting
into web development in school. I
believe it was in in 9th grade uh when
we started learning you know HTML basics
and you know this generation these days
might not remember what the world looked
like back then. Uh but you know we had
HTML that was not what it is today.
Nowhere near as powerful but even then I
got hooked very very quickly. And uh I
just anecdotally I remember fondly
asking for a uh CSS book for Christmas.
My grandma had absolutely no idea what
in the world CSS is. Uh but she gave me
that little book and um I finished
reading that on Christmas Eve before I
even went to sleep. That was one of my
my moments where I really got hooked. Uh
Little Boxes. It's called very very good
CSS book. And uh since then I've always
wanted to work on the web. Deliberately
sought out you know jobs where I could
work on on the web. And yeah um I worked
at the small agency in Munich while I
was uh studying computer science and um
worked as a software engineer again
doing web work building web applications
for for our clients. When we talk about
your growth from IC4 to IC5 I see that
you you only killed it. I mean you did a
eee so exceed you exceeded expectations
you greatly exceeded you greatly
exceeded and then you got promoted when
you redefined expectations. I'm curious
like why was there no promotion in the
greatly exceeds case and what's the
story behind that?
>> Yeah, I think this is something that
I've spent a lot of time thinking about
uh back then when I didn't get the promo
in the half that I hoped I was going to
get it. I think at the end of the day it
came down to to one expectations miss
that uh at the end of the day blocked
the promo. So I think this was seen as
as important enough so that the room
felt like we wanted to wait another
another half to see that point addressed
or something around uh cross functional
collaboration at the time. I think I was
uh I was a little too pushy and too
forward and maybe a little bit too
insistent with some of my ideas that I
felt like this burning conviction was
something we should be doing, but this
is not how you uh how you should go
about getting your ideas prioritized. I
think it's it's totally fine to suggest
things. It's fine to advocate for them
viferously, but at some point you can't
overdo it. You know, there's a there's a
balance to be struck and I think I um I
was a little bit too intense there. you
were greatly exceeding because you were
landing all this stuff and you were a
machine in terms of the impact you were
having on the projects,
>> but you're saying there was some
concrete feedback from maybe a partner
or something like that that said it was
like a ding on your your performance
>> essentially. Yeah. And if you think
about it, the two are not contradictory
because as you know as a manager uh
ratings are about the impact that you
have delivered. So you look back at the
half the six-month period like it was
back then before we we went to annual
performance cycles. You look at those
six months and you determine what impact
you've landed and you can land a lot of
impact and you can do a lot of good
work. But promotions especially lagging
promotions are about behaviors. Are you
already exhibiting all of the next
levels behaviors? And if there's a gap
between what's expected at the next
level, well, that means you're not ready
for a promotion in the cycle and we can
reattempt a promotion attempt, you know,
next cycle. And that that was the reason
that I think I I didn't get my my five
promo during that that uh greatly
exceeds half. Obviously, I hoped I was
going to get it as I'm sure everybody
does. It was a This one was a bit of a
weird one because the next half where I
was thinking, "Okay, now now I'm going
to get it was the co half and during the
co half the company as a whole did not
promote anyone because was a weird
environment. It was the the early days
of the pandemic." Yeah. For reasons
decided by people and you know I wasn't
part of these conversations. We didn't
do any promos. So I also didn't get my
five promo until the end of 2020.
>> So as such a high performer, how do you
feel? I mean getting a great lead and
then no promo and then also the block
too.
>> I mean it can be frustrating right just
to be fully honest. Of course it can be
frustrating when you feel like you were
so close to getting it. You have or I
have worked hard on addressing the
feedback. I think I've really taken that
to heart. Uh and I've gotten lots and
lots of positive peer feedback saying
that it was a very clear change in
behavior much more the way that we we
think you know we should collaborate
between engineering and and other
functions. And you've addressed all
these things. kept delivering impact.
So, you did strictly more and addressed
everything and then comes this
companywide unconditional blocker that's
decided, I don't know, like 11 levels
above my pay grade, right?
>> What do you want to do? You know, um
yeah, it was it was frustrating, but at
the end of the day, our careers are
long. So, this one half difference
really doesn't make a big difference. I
think the one thing I did tell myself
though is that even though I didn't get
this promotion at the time, although I
really wanted it, that I I didn't want
that to inhibit my learning or my growth
as an engineer. So even though I still
wasn't an IC5 by the end of the first
half in 2020, I was taking on work that
was clearly above the IC4 level. And at
the end of the year when we when I got
my my PSC, uh that was recognized fully.
So it all worked out in the end. maybe
took a half longer than I initially had
hoped.
>> I I lived that same experience as well.
I was I was hoping for a promotion and
then it got blocked. But I think that
that mindset is uh helpful and
productive. Even you know co's one thing
but people's promos get blocked for a
variety of reasons but there's no reason
on paper why you can't think about the
future or your growth or whatever. So if
you're an IC4 who's obviously doing IC5
things but you know your promotion gets
blocked because of uh let's say budgets
or something out of your control
>> right
>> you can think about what's the IC6 thing
to do
>> and that [clears throat] will just give
you a sense of progress still and like
something to achieve and it's just all
on paper the promotion is not a big deal
>> well and I would argue you almost have
to do this or you really should be doing
this because you can't be defeist and
you can't take understand the stance
that oh okay well I didn't get this
promo now so um I'm going to just be an
IC4 then and no longer exhibit the
behaviors that I need to demonstrate at
IC5 and then only when they make me an
IC5 will I will I do that
>> that's not how lagging promotions work
right
>> you know you get promoted once you have
for a sufficient period of time
demonstrated next level behaviors next
level impact
>> after the co half you got the
redefineses expectations rating and the
promo I'm curious like what is the the
story behind the thing you landed.
>> Yeah, I think at the highest level it
came down to me taking on or taking a
leading role on a project that has been
clearly classified as an IC6 level
project as an IC4 and landing that work
successfully. So in a way that is not
even the next level's expectations and
next level scope but that was the next
next level that we were looking at. was
a really big web project that was very
front- end heavy. So, right up my alley,
if you will, but it involved way more
people than just myself. This was a
project that had, I don't know, like
more than 10 people, more than 10
engineers contributing to it. And then
other partners like product managers and
designers and all the other roles that
that you find in product teams usually.
And for an IC4, I think that was that
was going above and beyond what is
expected at IC4. You know, you talk
about these different granularities or
these different sizes, these different
scopes that you should be looking after
and you you gradually work your way up
from a task level to maybe a small
project level, a larger project level,
something influencing the org,
influencing the an entire system, the
company, the industry. So, you work your
way up from like three to eight. Yeah, I
got recognized for this effort because
it it clearly was more than what was
expected of a four. We delivered all of
this on an ambitious timeline working
through what was a weird environment.
Again, it was the early pandemic. Uh and
then you know the summer of 2020, end of
2020. And we launched without any major
issues. So at the end of the day, all of
that also still matters. So you still
need to demonstrate all of this
operational excellence when you when you
work on these projects, right? It's not
enough to write a lot of code and say
it's done and then you pull the trigger
on launch day and you just cause a giant
incident and and break all the systems.
You're not going to get a pat on the
shoulder for that. So there's still
release hygiene that needs to be
observed. But it isn't just engineering
and I want to be um really clear about
this. It isn't just engineering when you
talk about an IC6 project. There's
usually ambiguity in some form that
could be in the product space where it's
not entirely clear what needs to happen
or what the the target outcome looks
like. There's people problems that you
run into. You need to coordinate, you
know, 5, 10, 15, however many people
contributing. Somebody needs to hold
that show together and and divide work
streams, make sure everything's on
track, run the weekly operational
meeting, report sideways and upwards and
and all that that stuff as well. And
yeah, I think at the end of the the year
when my case was being discussed, I
think it must have been pretty clear
that this wasn't an IC4 level
performance. I can I can really only
speculate. I don't know if this is how
we look at what differentiates maybe
like an exceeds from a greatly exceeds
or greatly exceeds from a redefineses,
but there is something there about okay,
if you're doing the next next level's
work, you're not meeting or probably not
even exceeding expectations. You must be
above that,
>> right?
>> Right. because it's so far outside of
what's what's expected at um at IC4.
>> Yeah, I mean intuitively that makes
sense cuz if you were an IC4 doing IC5
stuff, it's definitely going to be
exceeding. But then what's IC6? What if
you did IC74?
>> And it feels so weird to talk about this
because I feel like I'm tooting my own
own horn here quite quite a lot, but
it's it's I'm not trying to do that. I
think it's more about here's what's
expected and then if you really go above
and beyond this is what gets you to an
exceeds. I think we call that lading in
these calibration conversations where
you can clearly explain okay this is the
work that this engineer did to get to
their meets all
>> but then on top of that they did this
and we think this now warrants an exceed
and you can ladder your way up and you
can you can articulate why this rating
is is possibly justified so that other
people can understand. You mentioned you
were an IC4
trusted with the IC6 project. That's
kind of interesting to me because a lot
of people, you know, when you talk about
a promo and part of it is delivering on
something that is deserving of a promo,
but the other big part is getting the
opportunity to do something that's
worthy of a promo,
>> right?
>> What's the story behind you getting
either assigned to that project or
creating that scope?
>> Yeah, it's a great question. Um my
entire team catalog at the time was
working on this really really big
priority that had come up I want to say
quite suddenly in in 2020 and a lot of
people changed what they worked on at
the time and um you know we have a a
healthy level spread in the team
engineers taking on level appropriate
work but one one of the senior engineers
on the team was out on paternity leave
at the time so He in a way left a gap
that needed to be filled. So the
engineer who would have probably been
trusted with a project that ended up
coming to me had to fill that spot and
he was one level or even two levels
higher than me at the time than I was.
In a way it was a bit of a domino effect
where there was a bit of a vacuum that
needed to be filled and everybody in a
way took on N plus1 work if you will. Uh
and this is how I ended up with this
project. Obviously um it's not like
managers sit in a room and then they
roll the dice and that's you know
whoever gets the project. This is not
how it works. Obviously there's a bit of
luck that's always involved in getting
matched with the right opportunity. But
I firmly believe that you can increase
your luck surface area so to speak by
doing the right things. So if you
position yourself as in my case a web
person who wants to be the web platform
lead in my area, you know, on my team or
whatever the scope was at the time, and
then there's a big web project coming
up. Well, okay, they're certainly going
to consider me.
>> Doesn't mean I'm automatically going to
get it, but at least I I'll hopefully be
in in consideration unless it's like way
above what I can handle.
>> You had been greatly exceeding
expectations before. So you're the
manager or whoever is in charge of
figuring out how to staff that they
looked around and I mean web you subject
matter matter expert greatly exceeding
hungry to take on more. Okay, let's give
it to that guy. Um and I mean it worked
out. You you crushed it. So
>> uh good [laughter]
>> very hungry.
>> Is that something that's been true
throughout your career? you've been
quite ambitious or
>> yeah pretty much since the very
beginning at some point when I I think I
I vividly still remember the day that I
really got hooked I think it was like
something that clicked in my head when I
was learning JavaScript and I understood
if statements and loops like deeply
properly
>> right
>> something in me just went like oh my god
I am going to be like a demigod I can do
whatever I want to do and the machine is
at I my disposal and I I control it.
There was like this this feeling,
>> right?
>> And then as I mentioned before, I've
always had this interest in the web just
because I feel like it's I look at it
and I think it's a beautiful invention.
You know, this initially this set of
connected documents that shares the
world's knowledge. You know, you carry
around this mobile supercomputer in your
pocket and all you have to do is pull up
Wikipedia and you have this incredible
source of information available with
these beautiful blue links that you can
click to go to the next page. I just
think there's something philosophically
beautiful about that.
>> After you got thrown to IC 5, your
career trajectory actually went even
faster. Like when I look, if I were to
plot it, it' be like a little bit of a
hockey stick. You were at IC4 for a
while ratings and then you you jumped
and you jumped and you jumped. I'm
curious about the story behind the IC6
promo is another redefineses
expectations rating which is even
harder. like you know I could redefine
expectations as an IC3 right now you
know doing it as a IC5 IC6 I it's
starting to get a lot crazier so what
was the story behind the IC6 problem it
always comes down in some way shape or
form to the impact that you land impact
can come in many different forms depends
on the team you're on it depends on the
type of work that you do right but at
the end of the day you have to have
delivered a lot of impact as an IC5 I
was working on a project which I think
was part of the part of the reason that
I got the the six promo that had a lot
of again time pressure behind it. I
think we're we're on to a little bit of
a theme here where it was again another
web project with a very tight very
aggressive timeline and in this specific
case there was a hard deadline because
this project was part of a bigger uh
investment area part of a bigger puzzle
and had that piece not landed other
pieces couldn't have landed either that
impact could not have materialized. So
there's a lot of pressure because you
need to really deliver that come what
may. There are a few things that you can
influence or a few things that you can
change, a few variables, a few knobs.
And what are those usually, right? Like
what do you do when there's a project
that needs to get done quickly? You can
add more people to it. And sometimes
that does speed up the project to a
degree, not always. You can try and cut
scope, so you just try and do less. You
can lower the quality bar and be happy
with something that's that's high
quality, scrappier, not as well done, or
you can give yourself more time.
Usually, you can't do all of the all of
the above, right? We couldn't add time.
It was a hard deadline. Adding people
wasn't an option because we already had
like everybody was already allocated to
a high priority area. I had a handful of
other people working with me on this,
but this was it. So at this point you're
trying to manage carefully and
tastefully scope and quality and you
don't want to reduce whatever you're
delivering to just this absolutely
minimum MVP that has you know like a
shadow of what it should be and you
don't want to lower the quality bar too
much. I mean sometimes you
[clears throat] have to make a
concession or two right but I personally
always try to keep the quality bar very
high. I would much rather cut back a bit
of scope but make sure that whatever we
do ship we ship with well performance,
reliability and design craft and and
everything that goes into the the
quality bucket and we did that with this
project again on this short timeline
delivered this project and I think the
the specific call out there I was
actually rereading my um my feedback
that I got for this half this morning
just to remind myself the specific
feedback for me there was that there was
a high amount of ambiguity
And everybody at the time was super
stretched. So there wasn't uh there was
PM support, product manager support, but
not full-time, not as much as we we
needed it. And there were questions to
be answered and questions to be answered
quickly because otherwise for sure we
would have missed that timeline. So I
got a lot of credit for flexing into
that product hybrid role, that product
hybrid archetype I was mentioning. And
um what that means specifically is you
have this fog of war situation. If
you've ever played Age of Empires, you
know, you start in the middle of the map
and around you there's just like the
black void you need to go explore. And
uh we had that fog of war. We needed to
figure out what we wanted to do, what
needed to get done, scope that out
clearly, get alignment with product
management, engineering management, make
sure that other people are bought in and
and are happy about that. And then once
that is decided, at some point it
becomes a bit more operational. And then
it becomes about okay, how do we
sequence the work? How do we how do we
measure success? So when do we know that
we're done? What is good enough? What
isn't good enough? And then at the
lowest level, uh it comes down to, you
know, assigning work to people, fleshing
out these work streams, and then um
taking off the product hybrid hat,
putting on the coding machine hat,
putting on headphones, [laughter]
uh and going to town. Coming off of such
a high, you you actually switch teams. I
wouldn't expected like a team switch
when everything's going so well. So why
what's the story behind transitioning to
IG web right after that and why?
>> I think it comes down to changing
changing directions I guess or changing
priorities rather on my wider team. I
had realized over over my first uh what
was it at that point two two and a half
years at the company no longer almost
almost four years at the company
>> that I really enjoyed working on these
web projects and that I really enjoyed
working on anything related to quality I
I alluded to this earlier but work like
performance reliability delight and
craft when it comes to the design
aspects of things and it didn't that
didn't fully align with the priorities
that were coming in at the time. Web
just wasn't part of the the big priority
we were shifting uh and looking at other
things in my wider team. So it didn't
feel like this was the environment I
should place myself in if I wanted to
further pursue a career in that
direction. Right? I was kind of yeah
pretty deliberately working towards
being this web expert. That's how I
wanted to to shape my my career, right?
Because there's many different
directions you can go in. You can can
push to become a generalist. You can
push to become a specialist. You can at
some point want to become a TL, an UTL,
maybe explore management. But for me, it
was I want to be a web subject matter
expert and just build the best web tools
that I know how to build. And at the
time, uh Jake actually, who I believe
you've had on the podcast before, um was
hiring engineers onto the Instagram web
team. And I saw that vacancy and uh
jumped onto it. Met him over VC. uh
talked about the team, talked about what
work was coming up on Instagram web and
lo and behold it was fully aligned with
all of the things I just mentioned.
>> They had just done a big migration
project changed uh tech stacks in a way
and uh there was a lot of quality work
falling out of that and I had expertise
in this area. I loved the web and
Instagram is a great org to work in so I
felt like this is almost too good to be
true. had the conversations with the you
know engineering hiring managers but
yeah ended up joining the team and kind
of continued on that trajectory on
Instagram web. So at the time we were
doing work on many different surfaces on
Instagram web. Um I picked one when I
joined that wasn't taken yet at the time
which was uh notifications. So the if
you know the sidebar that you have on
Instagram web there's the notifications
panel that slides out that shows your
you know who liked your posts and
whatnot. And I worked on that basically
fully rewrote that cuz that code hadn't
been touched in many years. Hadn't
evolved and a lot of a lot of the code
was just getting really really old and
out of sync with the native apps as well
and landed all sorts of of um changes
there that were very very gratifying to
me if you will. I worked on that and I
felt so proud of the work I was doing. I
was so happy that this was what the team
wanted. They wanted somebody who um who
cared a lot about UI craft design craft
is valued a lot uh in Instagram and yeah
then worked on Instagram web for I want
to say about a year doing various
quality related things. I mentioned the
notifications panel that I worked on but
this was I think the the main product
change that I landed
>> most of my work actually was in the
product infra or client infra as we call
it. So it's not quite an infra level
job. So it's not like you know a true
infra teams ownership but product infra
sits in between product and infra as the
name suggests. So it's basically a lot
of it is uh when you think about
Instagram web basically what is the
architecture of the website that we use
to structure the code so that everybody
who's building on Instagram web can be
productive can iterate quickly can
iterate with confidence that means
there's the right level of safeguards
type checking tests right manual and
automated what have you uh and this is a
space that I have always been interested
in because it's a very leveraged area to
work in and I also think the more senior
you get the more you need to look for
these leveraged areas that you can work
in because at some point it becomes even
if you're a coding machine it becomes
quite hard to to deliver strong IC5
strong IC6 strong IC7 level product
impact because what does that even mean
like what is what is an you know an IC7
product impact quite high the
expectations so I found this product
infra to be uh an area that I find super
interesting and conversely there's many
engineers especially the very product
focused ones
who don't find it that interesting, who
would much rather do the the actual
product work, if you will. But yeah,
I've spent a lot of time improving our
our systems there.
>> So, you mentioned leveraged. I think
that's a really interesting concept. Can
you explain the the idea of what you
mean by leveraged?
>> Yeah, we talk about this um a lot on our
info teams, I think, when we talk about
the pit of success. What is the right
set of defaults or the right
architecture that you can put in place
so that somebody who is you know bright
and well-intentioned but maybe doesn't
have expertise in this area yet or maybe
doesn't have a lot of experience working
on the surface comes in and hopefully
just does the right thing because the
framework encourages the right uh way of
building product or the right tools are
in place to help uh with testing
whatnot. One specific thing that that I
did early on when I joined the Instagram
web team was to test the reliability of
the site uh specifically on the front
end. So I'm not talking about the back
end now. I'm talking specifically about
the front end. So in in React we have
this concept called error boundaries
which you can imagine are like try catch
statements about specific pieces of the
UI. So you can basically fence a certain
area of the UI and you can say if
there's any rendering errors happening
in this area render this fallback state
when that happens. And the way I picture
er rendering errors happening right when
an error gets thrown it's almost like a
little grenade that detonates and now
the question is how aggressive is the
blast radius how big is the blast radius
when there's a little rendering error
somewhere on the side in some area that
isn't like super important for the page.
Are you really happy like blowing up the
entire page and just showing like oops
something went wrong and taking down
Instagram web? Probably not. You
probably want to fence that. So I went
in and had a lot of fun just opening the
developer tools, clicking around
different areas. Uh and we can trigger
these errors in in any component we like
just to feel out like what would happen.
Yeah, this is the the reliability
effort. You can like argue that this is
maybe more like IC4 IC5 level work at
this point. But as one of my previous
managers said to me, usually there's an
IC4, IC5, and IC6. And maybe even higher
way to go about almost any problem. And
in this case, you can obviously just add
one error boundary in one place and call
it done. At that point, you're probably
doing more IC4 style work, right? Or you
can do this work systematically where
you audit the entire site. You do this
in all places. You solve the problem
comprehensively. you dedicate, I don't
know, like a day or two or something
like that to it. Maybe bring in one or
two additional people and you just
harden the entire site against these
errors, even if they're not happening
today, right? That I say I would say is
more the the IC5 level expectation. But
then you want to push that further
because when you're IC6, you can either
be a successful IC6 as a coding machine
by just doing an ungodly amount of IC5
work or you do IC6 level complexity. You
take on IC6 level complexity. And um you
can probably tell I have a lot of
opinions on this topic. I I think this
is very important to build reliable user
interfaces. I spent some time writing
everything down. Everything that I'm
telling you right now, I spent some time
writing that down in a big note that we
can share internally. Teaching people
about everything that I just said about
like here's how you open the developer
tools and here's how you trigger an
error in a random place. And then I also
took some time to to try and classify
these errors and say okay what is what
is the primary information on a screen
what is secondary and what is tertiary
and what do you want to do in each case.
So how do you want to handle a primary
piece of information missing because of
an error? A secondary piece of
information missing and a tertiary one
missing. And I think that way you can
have a lot of impact through setting
direction and suddenly me spending this
time helps the entire company. Anybody
reading this note can now apply this to
their own products that have nothing to
do at all with with Instagram web. And
now you can see how we go from fourle
impact to five level impact to six level
impact. If I'm understanding correctly,
that's where the leverage was in the in
the IC6 example was that you empowered
others to do useful work on your behalf.
Um they can go on and either prevent
those issues from coming up in the
future or fixing them themselves. And if
you did that for 100 engineers, then you
know it's just faster than you could
have done it yourself,
>> right? And it's it's scaled, right? I
cannot possibly be expected to know all
of the web products in the company and
go in myself and and work on a product
that, you know, doesn't even fall in my
org. But there's there's other things
you can do. You know just to complete
this example you can think of adding uh
lint rules to your codebase so that if
you have a specific anti pattern that
you can identify you can tell engineers
right in their IDE before they even
submit their diff tell them right in the
editor like hey you're doing something
we didn't find an error boundary that
protects you from bad breakage you
probably might want to add one here I
see so and then in this case the tool is
doing useful work on your behalf and
it's helping you scale and that's
expected of IC6 right And then I would
say this problem is solved sufficiently
well that I don't need to keep
dedicating my time to it. I can move on
to the next thing and maybe now that
we've talked about reliability, right? I
can start focusing on what performance
next or something like that. Going back
to your career story, it sounds like you
came on to IG web super great uh like
intrinsic motivation fit like you it's
exactly the problems you want to solve.
Great team, great culture and your
performance showed as well. you were
greatly exceeding even with the team
switch which you know usually causes
some thrash and then I saw that you
started to work on threads web and you
know I'm just so curious about all the
stories behind that so yeah how did you
start working on threads what's the
story there
>> threads web has been such an amazing
journey honestly uh I'm not paid to say
that it's just genuinely been one of the
most exciting
>> I'm not paid to [laughter]
>> well I'm paid to work on it but I'm not
paid to sit on the podcast and and tell
everybody how how great it was like
right
>> um
>> but seriously it's been a bit of a
roller coaster in some way because it
was an intense period of time but I look
back at uh the time that I spent on
threads web with the other engineers
working working on threads web and I
think collectively this is up until this
point at least the best work we have
done in in our careers and I again I I
don't say this to try and brag about it
it's just it's been such a a unique
environment to see a zero to one app
launch to be there from in my case
almost the the very beginning I got
involved uh a few weeks after the
project had gotten kicked off. So it was
all very secretive internally at the
time. It's just something that you don't
get to do statistically when you join a
company like Meta. You know we don't
create these new family of apps as we
call them apps almost ever. We try
different things. We create new products
over the years. How'd you get recruited
to the threads team? It was my manager
reaching out to me and um and suggesting
that hey there's this uh kind of hush
hush project going on. A small group of
people is trying something. I don't know
a whole lot about it, but I'm happy to
connect you if you're interested. I was
interested at least wanted to hear what
this is all about. Um got connected to
the the hiring manager on threads who
ended up being my my manager when you
know I fully joined afterwards and we
talked about what was required.
Initially the scope was quite small that
we thought about for web for threads
web. Um I later helped grow that into
more scope. Um initially it was all all
relatively confined, relatively small I
would say. But yeah I got involved and
um got started working as the the only
engineer on it for the first 6 to 8
weeks. So the almost the first two
months I was by myself working on web.
And it's again not something that you
usually get to do because it even feels
a little bit weird. you know, we we have
this big repository um that has most of
our web code internally. And I sat down
and I thought of a code name for the
project because we we have to have these
unique file names. So, you have to pick
a a code name that's unique. Picked
ended up picking the same one that they
had picked on the the native apps side.
And then I went rightclick new folder
and typed in that code name and started
from from there. And that's just a very
very rare thing to be doing. And I'm I'm
honestly I'm very happy and very glad
that I got to see it from the very early
days and I got to make some of these you
know big decisions. Um in hindsight I
kind of wish I had picked a different
shorter code name. I have typed that
name I don't know tens of thousands of
times now. [laughter]
Wish I had picked one that has slightly
fewer characters in it. But here we are.
>> You literally started threads from
scratch. It's such an unusual project.
>> It's very unusual and it's not something
that was clear from the very beginning.
Again, it is one of those direction
setting decisions that you have to make
at some point, but you want to make that
decision well reasoned. You really want
to be sure that this is the way you want
to be going. Initially, when we were
just uh I say we, at that point, it was
just me. Um, initially when I was just
starting to render, you know, something
just get the first component to show up
successfully on screen. I actually
started in the Instagram web codebase
and I just applied a little bit of CSS
to hide everything that was on screen.
But it was clear that this wasn't the
way to go for threads, right? So at that
point I decided, okay, the cleanest
separation to prevent any like bleed
over any any mix between the two was to
just say, okay, let's just create a
different folder. Let's create different
components. Let's just make it a
different surface, if you will. We
didn't know the final product name at
the time. We didn't know the final
domain, but we knew it was going to be
different as a surface from Instagram
web. So, it's not like we added a tab to
Instagram web. You know, at some point
when, for example, reals got added, we
just added one tab, but that's still on
Instagram web. Uh, this was a a
different surface entirely. You know, I
saw that year you got, which is even the
most impressive thing. You got another
redefined expectations rating um promo
to IC7. I imagine a large part of that
was because of how successful Threads
was and you know you were an
instrumental part of that. Is is that
the story behind the IC7 promo there?
>> Yeah, ironically you would think that as
you get more senior as you get higher up
or at least maybe maybe I I thought that
beforehand. You'd think that the writing
yourself review for the performance
cycle, the annual performance cycle
would become harder because you have to
justify your work in a different way and
maybe it is less clearcut. There isn't
as much a template of what a successful
IC7 looks like versus a successful IC4.
That's pretty well defined in
comparison. Ironically, for me, this
was, I think, the easiest self-re that I
ever submitted. The work wasn't easy at
all. It was an intense year. There was a
lot of stuff going on. We had this
Tomaltus launch and everything that came
out of it and it didn't it didn't stop
with me, right? Like I wasn't the only
one building threads web. I was the the
first engineer on it, but then a few
weeks in, we brought in a handful of
other engineers and at some point we
staffed a small team around it. Hired an
em, hired a PM, had a a full team
together, right? We also didn't stop at
a logged out web client. So we didn't
just have a loged out surface where you
can share a post or look at a profile or
do like an embed on a different website.
Um but we actually built a loggedin
client. So you go to you know at the
time threads.net these days threads.com.
Uh you go to threads.net you click login
you sign in and you see your feed and
you see your notifications and you have
settings and you can search and you can
post. So we had to build a loggedin
client. And at the end of the day it was
a relatively easy story to tell. Again,
the work wasn't easy, but the story was
basically, okay, we're doing threads.
Threads needs web. I came in, laid the
groundwork, created these like
foundational uh structures, hired the
team, ran the team as as the TL, put out
a lot of code myself during this time.
So, again, coding, machining under time
pressure. We're on web. We're on to
something here.
It's basically the third time, right,
this happened. Um, but it all worked and
we launched without major issues. the
product was wellreceived and um that
made for a pretty easy to tell story in
the performance cycle.
>> That makes sense. I can imagine your
performance review, you know, under the
impact you had just, you know, one line
is basically like instrumental in like,
you know, threads web tech lead led, you
know, x number of people that kind of
speaks for it. So,
>> right. And if that can be clearly
attributed to you as an engineer. So if
if your management chain and other
senior engineers who are who are sitting
in these conversations are convinced
that yeah it's clear that threads web
didn't happen you know like irrespective
of me or despite me but because I got
involved I think if you can create that
linkage and if that attribution is clear
you will you will get recognized for
delivering this impact. I I think that
um that's something that people talk
about sometimes like how do you get that
attribution especially when there's a
lot of other people working in the area.
It's it's difficult in general. I think
this is not an easy problem to solve
because you want to you want to have
clear ownership in general. I I really
do believe in strong ownership meaning
if I take on a problem space or if I
take on a product or a launch or a
feature or whatever size you have and I
am the owner of that feature product
whatever I need to own that outcome as
an engineer. So I need to make sure come
what may that this is going to be
successful and I think there's there's
many things that you can think through
that could happen to make the project
not be successful and you want to go
ahead and and get ahead of those. Talk
about threads web for example. Think
about the initial launch, right? Like
what what are the possible failure modes
in which launch day just becomes a a
clowny event and everything that can
possibly goes wrong goes wrong. Like
what what are those? And then you try to
work backwards from them and you try to
prevent them. Is there any questions
around the infrastructure maybe? Okay.
Uh let's talk to the right
infrastructure people and have them help
us verify that everything is set up
correctly. Right? It's we're talking on
the web. So suddenly, oh, we're setting
up an entirely new domain. We're not
setting up a new subdomain. We're not
doing, you know, threads.fas.com or
threads.instagram.com, threads.net. So,
is that setup correct? We really don't
want to launch and then have, you know,
DNS issues or something like that. And
you can go on like this. I think there's
a lot more failure modes you can come up
with and I would always recommend trying
to to get ahead of those as much as you
can. There's always a class of issues
that you cannot predict, right? So, you
have your known unknowns and then come
the unknown unknowns that you don't even
know, you don't know about. I think at
that point it becomes about operational
excellence, release hygiene. You want to
have error reporting that works. You
want to do a lot of QA and really test
your product, make sure it's it's
working fine. You want to have feedback
channels so when people tell you like,
hey, on on Thread's web, something looks
really funky in in this specific browser
that you respond to that quickly.
>> Sounds like you were thinking like, I
own, you know, whatever happens for
threads web and that led you to do all
these things.
>> Yeah, that's right. Um but maybe what we
should also talk about is that while I
was ultimately accountable for
delivering threads web because I was the
directly responsible individual you know
the DRRI that we always talk about it
didn't mean that I had to do it all by
myself that would have been impossible
>> so this is when you get into being a
senior engineer who works with other
engineers even as a coding machine like
obviously you need to work with with
other people I I couldn't have done this
by myself in in any way and at that
point you you think a bit about
recursive accountability if you will So
you just divide and conquer the problem.
This threads web overall I am on the
hook for making sure that this lands
well. But then we had other senior
engineers on the team who own meaty
pieces of the product and then they are
accountable for delivering that part.
But the way that meta thinks about these
from from what I'm understanding is that
even though there might be somebody who
owns part of the problem that doesn't
absolve me as the overall DRRi from you
know I'm still on the hook. that still
needs to work. And I I don't just get to
then say like, "Oh, but that wasn't my
sub problem. I only own the other
two/3s. This one/3 isn't on me. Blame
blame this." No, that's not how it
works. So, you need to find a way. Um,
and this I think is almost a bit of a an
art form as much as it is a learned
skill. How you can effectively work with
people, just be a great teammate, really
good TL who isn't micromanaging, but who
isn't off in the ether. Right? You need
to be applying the right level of touch.
Give people freedom to grow because
everybody has wants to do well for
themselves as well. They have career
aspirations. But you do also need to
convince yourselves yourself that things
are going well. I don't know who said
this to me years ago, but the metaphor
that I heard for this or the analogy is
a driving teacher like somebody who
gives you driving lessons early on. You
are driving, but they have a second
steering wheel and they have their hands
like right next to that. So the moment
you're about to slip, that's when they
intervene and they stop you from killing
the two of you in traffic. And then over
time, as you become a better driver, as
you know more, like as you become more
senior, so to speak, you gradually back
off. And then there's a a trust
relationship that's that's building up
this way, where over time, you know that
you have your your trusted lieutenants,
if you will, who who you can blindly
rely on. Yeah. I I think this is
something that every engineer who gets
to I would say like five but definitely
six plus needs to think about how to
influence engineers around him. How to
be a good TL that isn't like obnoxiously
close and and micromanagement
micromanaging every little thing. It's
tough
>> not easy. You know, I think if I asked
that question to someone who's a junior
engineer versus someone like yourself,
we would see a dichotomy because I think
you talk about ownership and you know,
assuring that others are successful and
scaling yourself and I think if I ask
someone who's uh right at the beginning
of their career, they might propose some
solutions on you got to hoard your scope
or you got to be the first one there or
you got to put your name on it. And
actually, it shouldn't matter how it
gets done, just that it gets done and
you play, you know, critical piece and
everyone can work together. Yeah. I
mean, that's the ideal, right? When
everything is set up and structured
well, you have the right owners in the
right places at reasonable levels,
right? You don't want to give something
to somebody that's way outside of their
comfort zone and just completely above
what they can do today. A little bit of
a stretch is fine, usually encouraged.
That that's how you grow. But if you
give something that's like three levels
above what they can handle, then you're
going to set up this person and this
project for up for failure. At the same
time, you don't want to give scope to
somebody for which they're just vastly
overqualified. But I do believe that
especially as a coding machine, not
every single diff that you land in
isolation has, you know, level
appropriate complexity. So if you pull
up a latest 10 divs from yesterday or
something like that and you audit them,
I doubt you would look at every single
one of those diffs and say like this
this looks like an IC7 diff. There's
like some maddening technical complexity
in here. But that's not the point.
Sometimes the point is like, okay, we
have this big problem.
>> I need to get this solved within the
next two weeks to unblock the next
workstream. I'm just going to lean into
my strengths for a week, sit down, crank
out 150 diffs, and get this thing
landed. I'm exaggerating slightly, but
at the end of the day, you will have
landed real impact because you're
preventing another project from
derailing or from going off the
timeline. Was every diff uh Shakespeare?
No, probably not.
>> So, it's a skill in your toolbox.
>> Yeah, exactly. And I think Jake talked
about this as well, if I remember
correctly, while while he was on the the
podcast and and said something similar.
You know, sometimes what's needed is
taking an Uber TL role where you hold
together these big work streams that
involve usually always different teams,
but at some point different orgs, you
know, and the further away the teams are
from each other organizationally, the
harder the coordination becomes. And um
sometimes what's needed is just look, we
know what we need, we need it tomorrow.
How do we how do we do it?
>> What does the future career planning
look like? like are you is it like let's
do IC8 or you know are you prioritizing
other things like let me find a new
interesting problem to solve? It's an
interesting question and I genuinely
don't have an answer today. I don't
know. Well, we'll see how it goes. I
know that the way that I'm operating
right now and the work that I'm doing
right now is extremely exciting to me. I
actually recently switched teams from
threads web to this big Instagram server
backend project team that uh Jake is
driving. So listen to his his podcast
episode if you want to learn more about
that. That is a big priority for
Instagram. So as I was alluding to in
the very beginning, you need to work on
something that's impactful. You you
simply do, right? You cannot be a
successful senior engineer and just work
on stuff that doesn't matter whatsoever.
About IC8 specifically, I don't know.
Um, maybe this is something that I'll
want to explore at some point. It's not
something I'm pushing for actively right
now, but I think there's obviously
growth to be had as an engineer to get
more familiar with different systems.
I'm actually going a little bit outside
of my my front-end comfort zone now and
I'm becoming more of a fullstack
engineer or working towards that. And
um, this is super exciting to me also a
little bit scary. Um, so trying to to
walk that balance as well. There's
always the the engineering management
track that I am not personally
considering for myself because I get so
much enjoyment out of the the work life
uh as an IC the coding of it all the the
highly highly technical nature of it all
those hairy problems you know the the
demigod feeling I was describing before
when I just feel like I can see the
matrix you know I'm I'm like Tron and I
can see can see everything by the way
secret recommendation secret tip uh The
Tron Legacy soundtrack is one of the
best soundtracks if you want to really
put on your headphones, get dialed in
and and get coding.
>> So yeah, we'll we'll see what the future
holds.
>> What about when you got promoted to IC6?
Was your first thought IC7 time?
>> No, I it definitely wasn't. That's what
happened when I got my promotion to IC5.
>> Yeah,
>> I celebrated for 3 minutes and then felt
like, okay, now we're we're getting
ready for for IC6 before dawn, you know?
That's that's it.
Um it definitely wasn't the case for
seven seven promotions are are quite
difficult. Um you said this before many
engineers don't make it to that level
but that that has there's many reasons
for that. You know there needs to also
be a business need for somebody with
that level of seniority. So if there's
no business need basically like an IC7
shaped hole that can only be plugged by
an IC7 shaped puzzle piece, you're going
to have a harder time making a case for
a successful IC7 promotion, right?
Right. And in my case, I think threads
web was um was a great opportunity that
came at the right time for me. The
criteria matched, right? Obviously, you
still have to always deliver these. I'm
not trying to downplay any of these
difficulties. Like these projects come
up,
>> but that doesn't guarantee a bromo,
right? You have to deliver them.
>> But if you don't get have these
opportunities because maybe they're just
not around, then it is much harder.
>> Have the expectations of the highest
levels ever scared you?
>> Oh, yeah. Absolutely. Absolutely.
Because when I joined as um an IC4, I
was thinking that okay, I will have to
eventually get promoted to IC5 cuz that
is the the company policy, right? You
need to eventually make it to IC5, which
is where you can then stop if you
choose. And I was kind of apprehensive
about IC6 because I had seen IC6s around
me and I wasn't sure that this was the
intensity I was I was looking for. I was
just like scared a little bit and I knew
for a fact with certainty that I never
ever wanted to consider IC7. And here we
are today and things came very
differently. And when I got to to IC6, I
had this conversation with my partner
and I said, "Okay, maybe maybe at some
point I might look at what it would take
to get an IC7 promotion and what that
would look like, but for a fact, I never
want to even think about IC8. We'll see.
Right now, I'm genuinely not pushing for
it because um it's not an easy jump to
make. There needs to be the right
position for it. And because I get so
much satisfaction out of the the type of
work that I currently do, I wouldn't
want to to give up too much of it." you
mentioned um maybe in just but 150 diffs
in a week and I'm kind of curious though
like you know as a coding machine what's
your your most insane
output week that you can ever think of
where you just you did something
ridiculous.
>> Yeah, I think that was the the threads
web year, right? That's what was the
year that threads launched. I think I I
came up just under 2,000 diffs at the
end of the year
>> for a year. [laughter and clears throat]
Uh, so you know, 365 days in a year
minus 100 for weekends or something,
200. Yeah, that's that's insane. That's
like 10 diffs a day
>> ish. Yeah. I mean, there's PTO, sick
days, on call meetings, whatever.
There's all of this other stuff, but
like roughly that's what you're what
you're looking at, right? And this is
again I I've had this conversations with
so many so many people over the years.
Um, obviously you can game the system if
you want to game the system. So at best
this metric is directionally
interesting,
>> right? There's in my mind no difference
whatsoever between somebody putting up
300 diffs and somebody putting up 400
diffs in a given half or in a given year
or whatever time frame.
>> There's no difference.
>> It's just like somebody tends to commit
like 20% smaller diffs and hence ends up
ends up with with more, right?
>> If you had the opportunity to talk to
yourself right when you had entered the
industry knowing what you know now, what
advice would you give yourself? I'd
probably try and tell myself that things
are going to be fine. You're already on
a good track. Don't put even more
pressure on yourself than you already
are. Um, I was very, very ambitious,
especially early on. I think I still am
to a degree, but now I think it's all
way more, you know, way healthier than
it was in the past. Um, you know, I
talked a lot on this podcast about my
love for for the web and development,
software development in general and
different technologies. And I was pretty
intense about it at a time. Um, I set
this rule for myself for years that I
would post one blog post every single
week and I stuck to that for quite a
long time and come what may, you know, I
was trying to juggle my university life.
I was doing my bachelors. I was doing my
masters. Was working at this agency for,
you know, not quite full-time, but
almost I was hanging out with friends. I
had a very timeconsuming hobby at the
time. Um, and come what may, if I came
home at midnight, I'd spend like 2 hours
until 2 a.m. and write a blog post if I
hadn't written one for the week. And
that is a level of intensity that I no
longer practice because I feel like that
is not healthy anymore. Um I think it's
fine when you're, you know, in your
early 20s and you're so hungry to go for
it and I think it's worked out well for
me. I think that because of all of this,
I think some recruiter at the time
reached out to me because I had
published all of the the stuff. So I
don't regret any of it. But I think the
advice I'd want to give myself is uh
this is plenty. Chill a little bit. It's
it's fine. It's going to be fine. Well,
what's interesting though is if you
didn't do that, you probably wouldn't be
in the position you're in now, though.
[sighs and gasps]
>> Would have, should have. It's, you know,
it's the wing flap off the butterfly. I
I don't know. Maybe. Yeah.
>> It's I I don't regret doing any of it.
It was the right thing for me. I never I
never hated doing it, you know. It's not
like I I set up this draconian regimen
for myself that I that I was, you know,
being crushed under. It wasn't that. Uh
but it was a bit of Tetris playing with
my calendar. There was a lot of things
that needed to be shuffled around to fit
everything together. But I learned a lot
along the way. Got a lot of practical
expertise from working at this agency
and and just having years and years of
web development experience alongside all
of the uni lectures which are way more
theoretical and partially outdated.
They're great for like the CS
fundamentals. You know, when you talk
about computer science topics and data
structures and algorithms and know your
time complexity and whatnot, operating
systems, databases, what have you. Math,
lots of math. But that isn't what I use
on a daily basis, right? like we're not
using lambda calculus, we're using CSS.
>> Yeah.
>> So,
>> well, you can relax now. You [laughter]
I7.
So, um yeah, thanks so much for sharing
your story with us.
>> Yeah, thanks for having me time.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to